[SPEAKER_00]: The first thing you have to answer is what happiness is for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Most people would just generally be going through life without even knowing what they want, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just follow things that make you feel good and avoid things that don't make you feel so good.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't necessarily mean that you're following happiness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just... it's more... it's more... you're just following an impulse.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the first step in finding happiness would be to recognize the difference between just going after things that might make you feel pleasant at the time, but not necessarily happy overall.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I think...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm sure many people are aware of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, if you stop and think about it, what is... what is it... what is it that makes me happy?
[SPEAKER_00]: You would not necessarily know, but you would know that things that you've been chasing up to that point are... have not resulted in happiness and contentment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's really where happiness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not being pleased with the current experience that you're enjoying, you know, with your friends or outdoors or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like
[SPEAKER_00]: Being perpetually contented with your own self, with your own well-being.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that takes work, takes effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not just a question of satisfying your desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, recognizing where the happiness lies, at least a direction where you could, where you have a better chance of finding it,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already a step towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, clarifying for yourself what you really want, what you really need, and also like using your past experiences to see which one of those actually made you made you happy, in a sense that you were happy with yourself, content,
[SPEAKER_00]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having a clear picture about that is certainly the necessary prerequisite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, probably, what you will come to realize is that most common notion, impulse-based notion of just chasing whatever present desire is, it's more often than not, not the reason for happiness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It often results in
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, people wanting more, people being unhappy, not contented, people pretty much becoming sort of more driven, which is not a state of ease.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, chasing senses, although might provide you momentary distraction, which pleasure you conflate for happiness, you would pretty quickly realize that that's not what happiness is rooted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Happiness is a state of mind, not really a state of satisfaction of your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, most people who would not have the clear notion of what happiness is, as an experience, they would naturally conflate of getting what I want, is what happiness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's just one way of going about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, not wanting anything that you can or cannot get, is also another way to be happy.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you... if you don't desire anything, you can't grieve over anything either.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize, okay, so it's a... happiness is a state of mind that I'm kind of responsible for.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might not be responsible for things that you get, things that you don't get, things that you had or then lost, things that you lost and then found back and so on, but you're certainly responsible for the values that you place upon those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether your values are placed upon getting the objects from my senses, sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, having a great time, and so on, or do you place the values on... on, like, eh... contentment of the mind, which often requires a certain ability to say no to your own self, to draw a line for your own self, because otherwise, it will just... the desires will just take you in these infinite directions of... that you can never satisfy.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's really the main key here.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, you know, how to find happiness, really, should be asked, like, how to understand what happiness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you understand what happiness is, even if you don't make any excessive direct effort towards it,
[SPEAKER_00]: You will already be going into that direction because you have certain clarity for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you would already have a clearer picture as to where to draw a line for your own desires, when to say no, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say you want something.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's already implicit knowledge whether that thing is necessary or it would just be like a satisfaction of this
[SPEAKER_00]: Insatiable thirst for sensuality, or it would just be a habit, pressure, or whatever else, and you know, it would probably be better if I were to say no to myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a hard thing to guess, because, as I said, it's already implicit, that knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's more like when people just habitually act out of impulse, they never notice these things, but it's not... you don't require some great mental effort and restraint to start seeing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the more you see it, the clearer it will become.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you will, as I said, so you will know where to draw a line.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, knowing what happiness is, is already a step forward towards the right contentment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, knowing where to... when to restrain yourself, and then taking responsibility for when you do allow yourself to engage with senses, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That will make the mind, well, more in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that brings to the second point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowing what happiness is, is the prerequisite.
[SPEAKER_00]: It sets the direction for you to develop a happy mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the development of happy mind is basically development of mind that's in your control, not other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the more control you have over your mind, the more ability to withstand it you have developed, the more contented you are with whatever circumstances life throws at you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there will be no...
[SPEAKER_00]: Things would be less challenging, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't mean everything would go your way, but means that when things don't go your way, when you don't get what you want, you will not lose perspective, because you haven't been blindly, habitually acting out of impulse at every whimsical desire that your mind threw at you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, knowing what happiness is, and then developing a certain self-control in regard to your own mind and your own mental state, and that means that's not a magical thing, that that self-control will not occur as a result of some magical recipe or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: The the self-control arises on account of effort that you put in to withstand the pressure of your mind and mental desires towards this, towards that, learning how to draw a line, learning how to say no, then enduring it and and growing out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so happiness is contentment, contentment with yourself and
[SPEAKER_00]: A degree of self-control that you have developed will be a degree of your ability to be happy, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: It almost corresponds directly.